José María Román

C/ Ricardo Clemares 40, portal 3 1° E E-28750 San Agustín de Guadalix (Madrid)

Spain

Tel.: +34 637 757 325 **e-mail:** <u>romanfau@gmail.com</u>

webpage: http://www.uam.es/josemaria.roman/

Summary

Laboratory and O&M Services Director in the R&D, Aftersales Service Center at Yingli Green Energy Europe. Project Researcher at Centro Láser UPM. Director of Photovoltaic Systems Quality and Control Laboratory for five years at INGENIA Solar Energy and CENER. Technical Manager of the glass-glass PV modules production line for BIPV. Implementation of the quality management systems ISO 17025 and ISO 9001. Ph.D. in Physics with two years research experience in the USA. Publications in international journals with referee. Five years living abroad. Fluent English.

Current Situation

Laboratory and O&M Services Director in the R&D, Aftersales Service Center

Feb. 2012-Present. **Yingli Green Energy Europe**. Madrid, Spain.

- O&M Services supervision, coordination with contractors and customers.
- Training courses for O&M testing of PV plants.
- Monitoring of BIPV system integrated in YGEE building.
- Installation of an off-grid PV system, and planned project in energy demand management.
- Aftersales and R&D project management.
- Product analysis and test in the laboratory and in the field.
- New tests definition and compliance with the guidelines of ISO 17025.
- Member of AENOR SC-82 for PV modules and systems normalization.
- PV plants technical due-diligence.
- PV module manufacturing facilities audits.

Professional Experience

Project Researcher

Feb. 2011-Jan. 2012. Centro Láser UPM. Madrid, Spain.

- Researched on the formation of metallic contacts on PV solar cells using laser.
- Operation of q-switched and cw-lasers, Confocal microscope, SEM and EDX spectroscope.

Director of the Photovoltaic Systems Quality and Control Laboratory

May 2007-Jan. 2011. **INGENIA Solar Energy**. Albacete, Spain.

- Quality control measurement of PV modules under international norms.
- Inspections and Performance measurements of PV plants.

José María Román 5 March 2018 Page 1/4

- Design and dimensioning of PV plants and production estimates calculations.
- Implementation of the laboratory quality management system ISO 17025.

Manager of the Photovoltaic Systems Service

Apr. 2006-Apr. 2007. CENER – Spanish Center for Renewable Energy. Navarra, Spain.

- Manager of the PV Modules Testing Laboratory.
- Manager of the PV Installation Design group.
- Implementation of the management system of the Service.
- Management of commercial and development projects.

Technical Manager of the PV module production line

Oct. 2004-Mar. 2006. Romag Ltd., Consett, Co. Durham, UK.

- Design of the lamination process for custom made glass-glass solar modules and standard glass-Tedlar modules.
- Definition of the production process for custom-made glass-glass solar modules, as well as for glass-Tedlar modules for qualification under IEC 61215 standard.
- Compliance of the production process with quality management norm ISO 9001.
- Training of personnel in the production process and operation of vacuum laminator and flash-tester equipment.
- Dealing with suppliers and customers.

Education

Senior Management Course (CADE)

Nov. 2009-Jun. 2010. **FEDA-Fundesem**. Albacete, Spain.

- **Objective:** To develop knowledge and basic skills for the overall management of a company.
 - o Strategic management: Strategic management and Economic environment.
 - o Marketing and commercialization: Marketing planning and Sales planning.
 - o Economic and Financial: Financial analysis and Management control.
 - o Human Resources and Management skills: Communication and People management.

EUREC Agency European Master in Renewable Energy

Oct. 2003-Sept. 2004. Universidad de Zaragoza. Zaragoza, Spain.

- **Introduction:** CIRCE, Universidad de Zaragoza, Spain.
 - o Introduction to the technical and socio-economic aspects of the Renewable Energies: Wind Power, Photovoltaic Solar, Thermal Solar, Hydroelectric Power, and Biomass.
- Specialization: Photovoltaic Solar Energy, Northumbria University, Newcastle, UK.
 - o <u>Physics</u>, <u>design and technology</u> of solar cells and modules, and design of <u>Photovoltaic systems</u>.

José María Román 5 March 2018 Page 2/4

- **Final Project:** Architectural PV solar modules production line: Process description and implementation.
 - o Jun. 2004-Sept. 2004. Romag Ltd., Consett, Co. Durham, UK.
 - o Design of the lamination process for custom made glass-glass solar modules.

Ph.D. in Physics

Oct. 1994-Oct. 1998. Universitat de Barcelona. Barcelona, Spain.

- Training in Quantum Field Theory, General relativity, Nuclear Physics, Stochastic equations and noise, and String Theory.
- Thesis dissertation: Low Energy Properties of Magnetic Systems.
 - Combined crystallography, optics and effective field theory to determine the dynamics of spinwave excitations and non-reciprocal effects in ferromagnets and antiferromagnets.
 - Applied a recursive numerical technique to compute ground state properties of quantum spin ladders.

Bachelor of Science in Physics, specialized in Solid State Physics

Sept. 1989-Jun. 1994. Univ. del País Vasco - Euskal Herriko Unibertsitatea. Leioa, Spain.

• Training in Crystallography, Lattice dynamics and phonons, Electronic structure and semiconductors, Quantum Mechanics, Optics, Dielectric materials, Group Theory and Particle Physics, together with several sets of related experiments.

Research Experience

Jul. 2001-Nov. 2003. <u>Instituto de Física Teórica, CSIC-UAM</u>. Madrid, Spain.

• Studied the cyclic flow of the RG and its effects in superconductors and spin chains.

Jan. 2001-Jul. 2001. Universidade de Évora. Évora, Portugal.

• Collaborated with ISTAS in the preparation of a program of scientific conferences.

Nov. 1998-Dec. 2000. University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. Urbana, Illinois, USA.

• Studied the suppression of the superconducting order parameter around magnetic impurities in *d*-wave superconductors.

Teaching Experience: Taught problems of the Eighth Semester subject *Nuclear Physics and Particles* (1998), and of the Second Semester subject *Classical Mechanics and Waves* (1995). Facultat de Física. Universitat de Barcelona. Barcelona, Spain.

Publications: Fourteen publications in international journals with referee.

<u>Seminars and Communications in Congresses</u>: Thirteen oral and two poster invited presentations in several universities and international conferences.

José María Román 5 March 2018 Page 3/4

Professional Skills

- Excellent organizational skills for the business administration complying with the quality norms ISO 9001 and ISO 17025.
- Extensive experience in solving complex problems through a combination of analytical, numerical and experimental techniques.
- Experienced in multidisciplinary work and quick adaptability to new topics. Quick learning ability and teaching ability.

Computer Skills

- Expert in office and calculation tools: MS Word, Excel and Access, TeX and LaTeX.
- Knowledge of Java, HTML (http://dftuz.unizar.es/), Auto-CAD.
- Strong experience programming in C++, FORTRAN, Python, Mathematica and Octave for the solution of problems numerically.
- Combined C++ code with FORTRAN and XmGrace libraries to obtain real-time graphical outputs.
- Monitoring application by reading and analyzing data with Python and MS SQLServer.
- Linux administration at intermediate level. User of UNIX (AIX, IRIX), Windows and Windows NT platforms.

Languages

• Spanish, English, and moderate knowledge of Portuguese, Catalan and Basque.

References

• Available upon request.

José María Román 5 March 2018 Page 4/4